Guide to the Keith-McHenry-Pond Family Papers, 1841-1961
The Bancroft Library.
Keith-McHenry-Pond Family Papers,
1841-1961
BANC MSS C-B 595
Keith-McHenry-Pond family
Number of containers: 23 boxes, 15 cartons, 2 oversize folders
The Bancroft Library. Berkeley, California 94720-6000
Include papers of William Keith relating to his career as an artist; papers of his wife, Mary McHenry Keith, reflecting her participation in the woman suffrage movement and humanitarian activities; papers of her parents, Ellen and John McHenry; papers of her sister, Emma Pond, and her brother-in-law, Charles Fremont Pond, relating to his naval career, 1876-1918; papers of the Ponds' daughter, Elizabeth Keith Pond, relating primarily to her interest in William Keith and to her travels and her camping trips in the High Sierra. Included also are miscellaneous papers of other members of the family and correspondence of Brother Fidelis Cornelius relating to his biography, Keith, Old Master of California.
Information for Researchers
Access
Collection is open for research.
Scope and Content
The Keith-McHenry-Pond Collection consists of the correspondence and papers of William Keith, his wife, Mary (McHenry) Keith, her father, John McHenry, her mother, Ellen Josephine (Metcalfe) McHenry, her sister, Emma (McHenry) Pond, her brother-in-law, Charles Fremont Pond, her niece Elizabeth Keith Pond and other family members.
These Keith family papers were given to The Bancroft Library by Mary McHenry Keith with numerous additions by Elizabeth Keith Pond and her estate from 1950 to 1956. Papers of Inez (Henderson) Pond, Charles F. Pond's daughter-in-law, were added by her daughter Mary Virginia (Pond) Culbertson in 1961. The collection relates to the careers and other activities and interests of various members of the Keith, McHenry, Pond and related families.
The key to arrangement which follows describes the collection in greater detail.
Biography
William Keith was born in Scotland in 1838. He emigrated with his parents to the United States where he became an apprentice to an engraver. In 1859 he came to California, became fascinated with its landscape and began to sketch and paint what he saw. His work proved to be popular and his reputation was soon established. The resulting financial success allowed him to study abroad several times. He produced hundreds of landscapes and portraits during his career, and his home in Berkeley became a meeting place for university professors, writers and artists. When his San Francisco studio was destroyed in the 1906 earthquake and fire, Keith began at once to replace the almost 2000 paintings which had been lost. He continued to work until a few months before his death which occurred on April 13, 1911.
Keith's second wife was Mary McHenry, daughter of John McHenry, a prominent San Francisco judge. Born in 1855, she graduated from San Francisco Girls' High School in 1875 and received a Bachelor of Arts degree in 1879 from the University of California at Berkeley. In 1882 she received a Bachelor of Law degree from Hastings College of Law, becoming the first woman graduate of that institution. She practiced law only briefly before marrying William Keith in 1883. Mrs. Keith was an early advocate of woman suffrage. She was an active member of many suffrage groups, including the National Equal Suffrage Association, National Woman's Party, Club Women's Franchise League of California and the College Equal Suffrage League, and was president of the California Equal Suffrage Association. In addition, she was an officer of the Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals and a trustee of the Latham Foundation for the Promotion of Humane Education. The years from her husband's death in 1911 to her own in 1947 were also spent preserving and exhibiting her sizable collection of Keith paintings.
Charles Fremont Pond was born in Connecticut in 1856. He graduated from the U.S. Naval Academy at Annapolis in 1876. In 1880 he married Emma McHenry, sister of Mary (McHenry) Keith. His naval career spanning over forty years, he became a rear admiral in 1912 and retired in 1918. He died in Berkeley in 1929.
Elizabeth Keith Pond, daughter of Charles Fremont Pond, was born in 1886. She studied art under Keith and began to collect material about him which she later used to compile a William Keith Miscellanea. She was a lifelong camper, skier, and hiker. After her father's retirement, they took long hikes throughout the high Sierra and other places in northern California. In 1945 she founded the Keith Art Association which was dedicated to promoting the appreciation, conservation and exhibition of Keith's paintings. She died in 1955 in her Berkeley home.
Key to Arrangement
- Papers of William Keith
  - Letters written by Keith, 1870-1910 n.d. (Box 1)
    Originals and typed copies, arranged chronologically. Written primarily to Joseph Worcester while travelling and studying in Europe. See also "A Family Story of Long Ago." Ctn. 1
  - Letters written to Keith (Box 2-3)
    Arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization. Correspondents of note are included in a partial list of correspondents which follows the Key to Arrangement. Unlisted letters are in an alphabetical miscellany in Box 2. Some folders include original letters with typed transcripts.
  - Letters of introduction written for Keith
  - Letters written to his son-in-law Edward Newell Harmon, ca. 1884-1919
    Relate primarily to the disposition of Keith's paintings.
  - Personalia, 1856-1883 (Box 4)
    Apprenticeship papers and certified copy of record of naturalization
  - Bills, receipts, etc., 1885-1910
    Primarily for painting supplies
  - "Statement of Assets," April, 1906
  - MS of "An Artist's Trip in the Sierra," 1875. Written for Overland Monthly. (holograph)
  - Notes for Lectures
  - Catalog of Exhibition of Paintings
  - Picture Lists and Inventories
    Compiled primarily by E. N. Harmon and Mary (McHenry) Keith.
  - Papers Relating to His Estate
    Will, inventories, etc. Copies.
  - Scrapbook, 1867-1882
    Kept by Elizabeth (Emerson) Keith?
  - Marriage Book, 1883
  - Miscellany
    Poems, membership cards, etc.
  - See also "William Keith Miscellanea," Ctns. 1-2 Clippings, cartons 13-14 Card Files, carton 14 Oversize Folder 1 B
- Papers of Mary (McHenry) Keith [Mrs. William Keith]
  - Letters written by Mrs. Keith, 1883-1947 n.d. (Box 5)
    Originals and typed copies, arranged chronologically. Letters, prior to 1898, are written primarily to Keith's daughter, Tennie, and other family members. Many later letters relate to her work for woman suffrage.
    See also "A Family Story of Long Ago." Ctn. 1
  - Letters written to Mrs. Keith (Box 5-13)
    Arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization. Correspondents of note are included in the partial list of correspondents. A miscellany of unlisted letters precedes each letter of the alphabet.
  - Copies of Letters of Condolence Following Keith's Death (Box 13)
  - Cards Accompanying Flowers, etc., For Keith's Funeral
  - See also Ctns. 3 4 for additional material
- Papers of John McHenry [Mrs. Keith's father]
  - Two letters written by him, 1838 1870 (Box 14)
  - Letters written to him
    Arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization. Correspondents of note are included in the Partial List of Correspondents. Unlisted letters are in a Miscellany at the beginning of the file.
  - Biographical Sketches
  - Receipts and Legal Papers, 1846-1875
  - Papers re His Law Library
  - Miscellany
  - See also Speech, Box 17 Clippings, Ctn. 14
- Papers of Ellen Josephine (Metcalfe) McHenry [Mrs. Keith's mother]
  - Letters written by her, 1847-1899 n.d. (Box 15)
    Originals, arranged chronologically.
  - Letters written to her (Box 15-16)
    Arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization. Correspondents of note are included in the partial list of correspondents. Unlisted letters are in an alphabetical miscellany in Box 15. Some folders contain both originals and typed copies.
  - Journal (Box 16)
    Records journey from Mississippi to New York and return, Mar. 25 -Oct. 31, 1846. Original and typed copy.
  - Diary, May-June 1842
    Describes daily life. Original and typed copy.
  - Receipts, 1847-1881
    Primarily re her book, The Wandering Jew.
  - Miscellaneous Notes
    Primarily re religion, Jews, etc.
  - Miscellany
  - Manuscripts of Writings (Box 17)
    - A Chapter of Recollections. Original and typed copy.
    - Rachael
    - Miscellaneous
  - Tear Sheets of Published Articles
  - Scrapbook
    Compiled by Ellen McHenry. Clippings -Obituaries of John McHenry and others.
  - Papers of John McHenry
    - Speech delivered in Sonoma, Calif. 1864
- Papers of Barbara Allen (Harris) Metcalfe [Mrs. Keith's maternal grandmother]
  - Letters written by her, n.d. (Box 18)
  - Letters written to her
    Arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization. Correspondents of note are included in the partial list of correspondents. Unlisted letters are in a Miscellany at the beginning of the file.
- Papers of Asa Baldwin Metcalfe [Mrs. Keith's maternal grandfather]
  - Letters written to him (Box 18)
    Arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization. Correspondents of note are included in the partial list of correspondents.
- Metcalfe Family Papers
  - Biographical and Genealogical Information (Box 18)
  - Legal and Financial Papers, 1835-1851
  - Miscellany
- Harris Family Papers
  - Genealogical Information (Box 18)
  - Miscellany
- Papers of Elizabeth Harris (McHenry) Lamare [Mrs. Keith's sister]
  - Letters written by her, n.d. (Box 19)
  - Letters written to her
  - Two Compositions Written By Her, 1864-1866
  - Obituaries and Resolutions Re Her Death
  - Invitations
- Papers of Emmanuel Benjamin Lamare [Mrs. Keith's brother-in-law]
  - Letters written by him, 1883-1912 (Box 19)
    Originals and typed copies
  - Letters written to him
    Arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization. Correspondents of note are included in the partial list of correspondents. Unlisted letters are in a Miscellany at the beginning of the file. Many letters are in French.
  - Writings
    Manuscripts and typed copies of short articles and a poem. Some written in French.
  - Bills and Receipts, 1885
- Papers of Caroline Goddefroy Lamare [mother of Emmanuel B. Lamare]
  - Letters written to her (Box 20)
    Arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization. Correspondents of note are included in the partial list of correspondents. Unlisted letters are in a Miscellany at the beginning of the file. Written primarily in French.
- Papers of Lamare Family
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 20)
  - Legal Papers. In French
  - Bills, Receipts, etc.
  - Death Notices
  - Miscellany
- Papers of Mary Emma Zuleika (Metcalfe) Hay [Mrs. Keith's aunt]
  - Letters written by her, 1875-1886 n.d. (Box 21)
    Arranged chronologically
  - Letters written to her
  - Writings
    Primarily typed copies of articles
  - See also Oversize Folder 1 B
- Papers of William Gilbert Hay [Mrs. Keith's uncle]
  - Letter written by him, 1864 (Box 21)
  - Letters written to him
- Papers of William Gilbert Hay [Mrs. Keith's cousin]
  - Letters written to him (Box 21)
  - Writings
    Article, "Ambition," 1884 (holograph); reprint of article, "Etiology of Zoster," 1898
- Papers of Emily Parsons Babcock Hay, d. 1937 [Mrs. Keith's cousin]
  - Letters written to her (Box 21)
- Hay Family Papers
  - Papers Re Estate of Emily Hay (Box 21)
    Inventory, decree of settlement, etc.
  - Financial and Legal Papers
  - Genealogical and Biographical Information
  - Miscellany
  - Writings of Emily Hay (Box 22)
    Primarily drafts and typed copies
  - Family Scrapbooks and Albums (Box 23)
    Autograph album, birthday album, scrapbooks containing clippings, obituaries, poems, greeting cards, etc.
  - "A Family Story of Long Ago" (Carton 1)
    Typed transcripts of letters written by William and Mary (McHenry) Keith. Compiled by Elizabeth Keith Pond. 3 volumes.
  - "William Keith Miscellanea" (Carton Ctns. 1 2)
    Typed transcripts of excerpts from letters and clippings and articles concerning Keith and his career; announcements and catalogs of exhibitions of his work; clippings, etc., re his friends, other artists, art, etc.; photographs. Some material concerns Mrs. Keith and woman suffrage. Compiled by Elizabeth Keith Pond. Mounted; in 25 binders arranged as follows:
    - ca. 1856-1872 (Carton 1, Volume v.1)
    - 1873-1875 (Volume v.2.)
    - 1876-1885 (Volume v.3.)
    - 1886-1889 (Volume v.4.)
    - 1890-1895 (Volume v.5.)
    - 1896-1899 (Volume v.6.)
    - Poems written to William Keith and to his paintings, mainly undated (Volume v.7.)
    - 1900-1904 (Volume v.8.)
    - 1905-1907 (Volume v.9.)
    - 1908-1910 (Volume v.10.)
    - 1910-1911 (Volume v.11.)
    - (Supplement). Medical record of last illness, Mar. 5 -Apr. 13, 1911 (Carton 2, Volume v.11.)
    - 1912-1914 (Volume v.12.)
    - 1915-1919 (Volume v.13.)
    - 1920-1927 (Volume v.14.)
    - 1928-1930 (Volume v.15.)
    - 1931-1933 (Volume v.16.)
    - 1934-1937 (Volume v.17.)
    - 1938-1939 (Volume v.18.)
    - 1940-1941 (Volume v.19.)
    - 1942-1943 (Volume v.20.)
    - 1944-1946 (Volume v.21.)
    - 1947-1949 (Volume v.22.)
    - 1950-1952 (Volume v.23.)
    - 1953-1955 (Volume v.24.)
    - Catalogues and Reference Papers. Bibliography, lists of paintings, etc. See also Card Files (Volume v.25.)
  - Papers of Mary (McHenry) Keith (Carton Ctns. 3 4)
    - Diaries, 1875 1883 (Carton 3)
    - Biographical Data
    - Poems and Tributes
    - Membership Certificates
      See also Oversize Folder 1 B
    - Manuscripts of Speeches and Writings
      Primarily holograph and typed copies, arranged as follows:
      - Co-Education. 1902 (Printed copy)
      - [College Equal Suffrage League]
      - Dress Reform. 1887
      - Is The Franchise a Privilege Or a Right?
      - The Origin and History of Wills. 1882
      - Suffrage Work of John Hyde Braly in Southern California
      - [Suffrage movement in California]
      - [Susan B. Anthony]
      - [Woman Suffrage]
      - Speech, Oct. 19, 1882, to Sons of Revolutionary Sires
    - Material Re Her Education
      - Class of 1879, University of California, Berkeley
        Clippings and other printed items re members, commencement program, photograph of class reunion, 1918, letters in reply to invitation to 1921 reunion, etc.
      - Hastings College of Law, University of California, Class of 1882
        - List of graduates, program for graduating exercises
        - Golden Jubilee, 1928, etc.
        - See also Oversize Folder 1 B
      - Lecture Notes
      - Miscellaneous Papers
    - Material re Her Interests in Humane Organizations
      Clippings and printed items re Society For the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals, Latham Foundation, etc.
    - Papers re Her Home on Ridge Road, Berkeley
      Specifications, drawings, inventory of furniture, etc., 1924, agreement re landscaping, etc.
    - Agreement with St. Mary's College
      Re publication of Brother Cornelius' biography of Keith, 1941
    - Notes re William Keith
      Includes lists of Keith paintings in her home
    - Miscellaneous Notes
    - Copies of Poems
      Written by various people including Timothy Rearden
    - Letterheads of Various Organizations
      Mainly suffrage groups
    - Invitations, programs, calling cards
    - Miscellany
    - Clippings, Tear Sheets, etc., 1896-1950 n.d. (Carton Ctns. 3 4)
      Primarily re woman suffrage. Mainly in scrapbooks.
      Clippings, Ctn. 14
- Papers of Elizabeth Keith Pond [Mrs. Keith's niece]
  - Letters written by her, 1904-1955 (Carton 5)
    Primarily typed copies relating to her compilation of the Keith Miscellanea and to William Keith in general.
  - Letters written to her
    Arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization. Correspondents of note are included in the partial list of correspondents. A Miscellany of unlisted letters precedes each letter of the alphabet. Some letters are written in response to requests for material about Keith.
  - Letters of condolence
    Written to E. K. Pond following the death of Mary (McHenry) Keith, 1947. Letters from more important correspondents have been added to their respective correspondence folders.
  - Art Work
  - Financial Papers
    Includes royalty accounts for Keith, Old Master of California, the biography written by Brother Cornelius.
  - Miscellaneous notes re Keith, Old Master of California
  - Programs, announcements, etc., for art exhibitions, plays, etc.
  - Records of loans, gifts, etc. of Keith's art work
  - Journals, pamphlets, menus, tickets, etc. re trip to Europe, 1937 (Carton 6)
  - Miscellany
  - See also Oversize Folder 1 B
- Papers of Charles Fremont Pond [Mrs. Keith's brother-in-law]
  - Letters written by him, 1877-1928 (Carton 6)
    Originals and typed copies, arranged chronologically. Many letters relate to his career in the U.S. Navy.
    See also Miscellanea in Ctns. 10 11.
  - Letters written to him
    Arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization. Correspondents of note are included in the partial list of correspondents. A Miscellany of unlisted letters precedes each letter of the alphabet.
  - Monthly Reports of Academic Work at the U.S. Naval Academy, Annapolis, 1875-1876
  - Speeches and Reports
    Typed copies, 1905-1918. Primarily re the Navy
  - Admiral's Flag
  - Naval Orders
    Certified copy, Nov.-Dec., 1916
  - Letters re His Appointment to the Puget Sound Navy Yard
    Typed copies, 1915
  - Membership Cards
  - See also Miscellanea. Ctns. 10 11 Journals, Ctn. 12 Oversize Folder 1 B
- Papers of Emma (McHenry) Pond [Mrs. Charles Fremont Pond]
  - Three letters written by her, n.d. (Carton 6)
  - Letters written to her
  - Letters of Condolence written to her following her husband's death, 1929
  - Manuscripts of Speeches and Writings (Carton 7)
  - Daughters of the American Revolution
    Application for membership, etc.
  - United Daughters of the Confederacy. Jefferson Davis Chapter
    Application for membership, financial reports, etc.
  - Material re "Constitution" - a card game she invented
    Box containing "Constitution"
  - Biographical Data
- Papers of Inez Virginia (Henderson) Pond [daughter-in-law of Charles F. Pond]
  - Letters written to her (Carton 7)
  - Financial Papers (Carton 8)
  - Announcements, Invitations, Programs
  - Miscellany
- Papers of Charles McHenry Pond [son of Charles F. Pond]
  - Two letters written by him, 1937-1939 (Carton 8)
  - Letters written to him
  - Papers Re Purchase of a Yacht
  - Death Certificate
  - Business Papers
  - Miscellany
    Pilot's license, etc.
  - See also Scrapbook, Ctn. 13
- Papers of John Enoch Pond [son of Charles F. Pond]
  - Two letters written by him, 1937 (Carton 8)
  - Letters written to him
  - Reprint of His Article, The Eruption of Krakatoa. 1936
  - Legal Papers
- Papers of Charles McHenry Pond [Charles F. Pond's grandson]
  - Letters written to him (Carton 8)
  - Miscellaneous Papers
- Papers of Mary Virginia (Pond) Culbertson [Charles F. Pond's granddaughter]
  - Two letters written by her, 1945 n.d. (Carton 8)
  - Letters written to her
  - Miscellany
- Pond Family Papers
  - Genealogical Data (Carton 8)
  - Miscellany
  - Invitations, Programs, etc. Arranged chronologically as follows:
    - 1895-1908
    - 1909
    - 1910
    - 1911-1913
    - 1914
    - 1915 Primarily for functions at the Panama Pacific International Exposition (Carton 9)
    - 1916-1917
    - 1918-1929
- Papers of Brother Fidelis Cornelius
  - Letters written by him, 1935-1945 n.d. (Carton 9)
    Primarily typed copies arranged chronologically. Relate mainly to his biography of William Keith.
  - Letters written to him
    Arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization. Correspondents of note are included in the partial list of correspondents. Unlisted letters are in a Miscellany at the beginning of the file. Relate primarily to his biography of Keith.
  - Notes, Newsletters, etc., re the Keith Gallery at St. Mary's College, Calif.
  - Miscellany
- Keith Art Association
  - Letters from the Association, 1946-1955 (Carton 9)
    Primarily typed copies, arranged chronologically. Written mainly by T. K. Cleveland, President.
  - Letters written to the Association
  - Internal Memoranda
    Re dues, publications, etc.
  - Miscellaneous Papers
    - Notices of meetings
    - Constitution by-laws
    - Financial records
    - Minutes of meetings
    - Membership lists
    - Publicity
    - Inventory of Paintings
    - Receipts
    - Copies of The Palette(bulletin)
    - Miscellany
    - See also Guest registers, 1945-1953, Ctn. 13 Clippings, Ctn. 14
- Miscellaneous Correspondence
  - Written to various people including a few members of the Keith family. (Carton 9)
    Arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization. Unlisted letters are in a miscellany at the beginning of the file. A partial list of correspondents follows the Key to Arrangement.
  - Miscellaneous Invitations
- "Charles Fremont Pond Miscellanea"
  - Primarily typed transcripts of letters written during his naval career. (Carton 10)
    Also contains official papers re his career, photographs of posts where he was stationed, and some family photographs. Compiled by Elizabeth K. Pond. In 22 binders arranged as follows:
    - 1875-1879 (Carton 10, Volume v.1.)
    - 1880-June 1881 (Volume v.2.)
    - July 1881-June 1882 (Volume v.3.)
    - July-Dec. 1882 (Volume v.4.)
    - Supplement. Apr. 1884-June 1885 (Volume v.4.)
    - 1887-1890 (Volume v.5.)
    - Apr. 1894-Apr. 1895 (Volume v.6.)
    - May 1895-Sept. 1896 (Volume v.7.)
    - 1896-1901 (Volume v.8.)
    - Supplement. Feb. 1897 -June 1898 (Volume v.8.)
    - 1902-1908.Includes photographs of the San Francisco earthquake and fire (Volume v.9.)
    - 1907-Mar. 1908. Mainly photographs of Alaska (Volume v.10)
    - 1908. Mainly photographs of Alaska (Volume v.11.)
    - Oct. 1908 -June 1909 (Volume v.12.)
    - July 1909-1910 (Carton 11, Volume v.13.)
    - Photographs. Undated. Mainly Hawaiian Islands (Volume v.14.)
    - Jan.-June 1911. Includes photographs of E. B. Ely landing his airplane on the deck of the U.S.S. Pennsylvania, Jan. 18, 1911. (Volume v.15.)
    - Oct. 1911 -Apr. 1915 (Volume v.16.)
    - Apr. 1915 -Jan. 1916 (Volume v.17.)
    - Jan. -Apr. 1916 (Volume v.18.)
    - July-Dec. 1916. Includes photographs of Port-au Prince, Haiti. [End of naval career] (Volume v.19.)
    - Sept. 1917 -Mar. 1929 (Volume v.20.)
    - Index and Notes (Volume v.21.)
    - Catalogue. Re scrapbooks, miscellanea, etc., compiled by E. K. Pond (Volume v.22.)
- "Mountain Journals"
  - Typed transcripts of letters written mainly by E. K. Pond. (Carton 11)
    Also contains photographs, drawings, etc. Compiled by E. K. Pond. In 4 binders, as follows:
    - Cruise to Hawaii, Guam and Japan, 1904-1905; cruise to Alaska, 1908 (Volume v.1.)
    - Camping trips to Yosemite and other parts of the high Sierra, 1901, 1912, 1914, 1915, 1917, 1919. Includes several photographs by Ansel Adams (Volume v.2.)
    - Hiking and camping trips in Yosemite and other parts of the Sierra, 1920-1925; hiking and camping trip up the coast to Scotia, California. 1921 (Volume v.3.)
    - Hiking and camping trips in Yosemite and other parts of the Sierra, 1926-1930; hiking trip from San Francisco to Santa Barbara, 1927 (Volume v.4.)
- Journals, Scrapbooks and Guestbooks
  - Three Journals kept by Charles Fremont Pond, Aug. 1877-July 1880, July-Aug. 1881, 1884-1888, relating to voyages to Hawaii, Alaska, etc. (Carton 12)
  - Three Scrapbooks of clippings relating to C. F. Pond, 1878-1911, 1911-1916, 1916-1942
  - Scrapbook of clippings relating to Charles McHenry Pond and aviation, 1911-1926